so this is a fun class not serious okay
and it's a break from the lamrim class
and we're continuing through a text
called Duncan shunt that argument
between the angel and the devil in one
person's mind and the devil is going to
teach us 25 useless meditations and we
finished eight so far okay and then the
devil says by the way I rarely see you
in people's mind who's that angel
understanding since you are like that
lotus flower that grows once every
thousand years and for you to even come
in a thousand years in somebody's mind
it takes our incredible amount of karma
and the only easy way to make that karma
is to help someone who's helping the
Dharma so who's spreading the Dharma
help someone who's spreading the Dharma
okay like a DCI organizer okay
pleasing your number who said that the
devil yeah the devil is smarter than
most of us okay devil understands wisdom
and he's tried to block it in the human
mind okay then verse 109 then in it
doesn't I
nobody has to practice for thousands of
years to make the Karma for me to come
in their mind because I was there from
the beginning
okay the devil is built into your mind
okay it comes from the factory okay then
the only way to hurt me is if someone
practicing meditation which is the
opposite of me okay which CeCe
okay verse 105 every person in the world
and once I am your friend you will never
have freedom okay all right okay
useless meditation number nine verse 111
okay so this says people have a mistaken
emptiness meditation and they tried to
stop thinking about anything okay and
this is called in Tibetan here
it's called DND men may say daeun demon
meant the end amendment
yeah it means just don't choose anymore
between this is one way or this is the
other way just let it go surrender
okay similar to meditation number eight
yeah
formulas room number four okay so here
is that meditation okay don't try to
think something is one way or the other
way just let God surrender to what comes
in your mind don't fight
relax let the thoughts come okay then
what's he say about this meditation this
idea is so bad I can't stop laughing
oh that's cool yeah don't think yeah
just surrender huh yeah I love it I love
it okay it doesn't make the devil
uncomfortable at all okay he's very
comfortable in the mind of a person
who's trying to think about nothing try
to decide nothing okay he says that kind
of meditation I can live with okay and
if you think it's a good meditation
you're just a joke in tibetan it's a
kammo short short means are like you're
not supposed to be laughing you're
listening to a stupid person talk and
it's a serious situation and and you're
like like if you go to the white house
and others
okaythat's card game or so haha okay all
right number but we are using it as a
ladder right we are going up to don't
stop before you hit number nine okay
in effective meditation number ten okay
verse 112 so some people say if the
things around us are empty right when
you reach the emptiness of your number
when you kick out what boo-boo Lama and
you just have like emptiness then
because that's empty
the object is empty then the subject
must be empty the mind itself must be
empty okay that's a different idea and
they meditate that the mind is like an
illusion okay
the mind is like not what it appears to
be and they think that's a meditation on
emptiness it's true that the mind is
like an illusion why in Buddhism we said
there are two realities ultimate reality
and deceptive reality deceptive reality
is called deceptive or illusion because
it fools you okay it makes you think
something wrong okay and everything's
like that it looks like your husband
decided to call you stupid it looks like
that you came home you open the door and
the husband's start yelling at you it
looks like he decided to yell oh it
looks like that so we say the world is
deceptive reality in that whole lion
stance meditation everything is
deceptive reality except for that when
you cancel the boo-boo Lama okay when
the boo-boo Lama goes away that's the
only thing that's even close to ultimate
reality okay emptiness okay everything
else is this scepter looks like it's not
coming from your seats looks like you
are meditating okay it doesn't feel like
seats are opening in your mind okay it
feels like you decided to meditate on
those objects but you didn't decide okay
it's just the Karma opened at the same
time as Geshe Michael was talking okay
no connection actually okay very
interesting right you're not meditating
that's why you have trouble managing
okay you are following the seeds from
last week you have to do what the seeds
say the seeds are the boss
you mind only school what are seeds
called chen-wong dominated dominated
okay you don't have a choice you are
dominated by the seeds okay what comes
up in your mind during meditation it's
not your choice it's a choice of what
happened last week okay if you are good
to people last week or you are bad to
people
last week you will have a good
meditation or not you cannot have a good
meditation
okay doesn't matter how you sit doesn't
matter what you eat okay doesn't matter
how much yoga you do so we should just
relax and eat pancakes that's my system
so if I imagine if I now this gets
difficult okay when you watch the Lama
coming out of the seeds in your mind are
you watching emptiness no you are
watching dependent origination okay
cause and effect okay that's a positive
thing
it's not a absence it's not something
missing it's a positive thing okay now
this guy in meditation and number ten I
think right he's watching his own mind
and maybe he's even understand that his
thoughts are coming out of seeds okay
which is correct okay
is it emptiness no okay now this is very
subtle okay
this is you have to be careful here he's
like watching the silver seeds open and
create the llama okay but it's not
enough
okay it's not enough is it useful yes is
it important yes do you have to do it
yes will it save you
no you have to push to the empty llama
you have to push further okay don't stop
at the eggs okay that's an important
step but it's not the goal the goal is
no boo boo llama no lama who's a mistake
okay no teacher who's a mistake okay you
have to go push push push push push
okay is it good to see the seeds open
yes
should you see the seeds open yes is it
emptiness no okay you have to push
further so the problem with this first
pension lamas text very very difficult
very subtle now he's like saying it's
not enough to see it seeds open you have
to go farther you have to push farther
you have to cancel the teacher who came
into your life by accident okay not
coming from you you have to cancel that
you have to think of it and then you
have to cancel it okay so that's a very
subtle
now listen in verse 113 ready Nick if in
a meditation you decided I didn't exist
then that would damage me that's an
emptiness meditation who's me yeah even
the devil in your mind okay to realize
you're wrong ideas are coming out of
seeds is correct but it's not enough you
see you have to imagine wrong idea that
came in your mind accidentally not
because you taught the wrong thing to
somebody else in the past okay wrong
idea that can come up in your mind
accidentally that wasn't because you've
made bad deed number 10 okay what's
badly number 10 don't understand the pen
okay so did the devil come in your mind
because you didn't understand the pen
yeah now does he come from his own side
or does it come from you yeah it comes
from me like a pen he comes from me
okay if I then how about the devil who
doesn't come from your sin doesn't exist
if you think about that he says here
that would damage me because I cannot I
cannot not be R and B here too I cannot
not be here and B here too if you see
I'm not real if you see I'm coming from
your sins if you see that the devil
who's not coming from your sins it's not
here then I can't be here okay so don't
go that okay don't do that until you
reach that kind of meditation where you
can see I'm not here and until the way
you think
and the way I think are fighting with
each other I'm safe I'm okay
okay I'm enjoying this mine got it
they said I shouldn't say nod your head
I'm supposed to ask if everybody really
got it okay yeah okay all right number
11 here starts a group of meditations
where we misunderstand naam cuttable st.
Uncle Tom
like space space like meditation this is
a famous Buddhist meditation okay
of course it means the absence of the
boo-boo Lama it's like space okay I got
it
all right it means that but some people
didn't understand that they close their
eyes they try to follow a lake ripple as
far as possible okay
space like meditation that's the wrong
kind of space okay that's the wrong kind
of space that's not Buddhist space
Buddhist spaces honking when we say du
space like meditation it means do a
emptiness meditation it doesn't mean
imagine sky is unlimited
okay got it so we're gonna have a few
mistaken meditations here that's why in
DC I we do mm-hmm
we do a four spaces meditation so that
people understand the first three are
not empty let's go through this for just
briefly and then they will come here
they will come in this persons list of
stupid meditations okay number one
such as such a Menon and General Erwin
do Tina such a concert analyst and I'm
continuing a semi monkey demand on
dimension and cement and non katana
governing Dylan Duncan Madiba Oh Abby
Tomoko sure some lololo Buddhists think
that space means the blue sky okay
that's the lowest one space is the blue
sky some I heard that minute some people
say go for a walk good stare at the sky
this is emptiness okay now you know it's
stupid but 99% of Buddhists have no idea
some Lama gets up and says stare at the
blue sky they're like yes Lama okay it's
a dumb idea why you can stare at the
blue sky you'll get all the old die
that's the end of it okay it doesn't
help you it makes you a little bit calm
it's cheaper to buy a beer okay last
time okay so it is space skylights numb
cut taboo but it's not the real meaning
okay now some people say oh that's not
space space is outer space okay where
the stars are the black stuff between
the stars
okay the black stuff between the stars
is outer space I'll tell you a funny
story about the Shanghai person who came
to Diamond Mountain first night they're
looking at war then they came to Michael
Dunn I think they said Michael Dunn what
will it come tomorrow also
okay so that if you haven't been to
Shanghai you don't understand
you can't see your hand in front on a
bad day they told us don't cry out of
the hotel we're like what happened
err anyway okay but I love Shanghai so
outer space black thing between the
stars is not the meaning of emptiness
okay
those two are easy why blue and black
are positive they are positive emptiness
must be something's missing
emptiness must be something's missing
in fact something that couldn't be there
is missing okay not something which
could be there okay now number three is
much more difficult number three is
space in the sense of safe space in the
sense of place does this cup take up
space yeah because the Clarke wants to
go there but he cannot this seat on the
airplane is occupied by some fat guy and
Clarke cannot sit there okay
then we take the cup out of the space
what happened to the space it's still
there okay place GPS coordinate you know
so many latitudes so many longitude it's
it's there okay it will always be there
if this planet is destroyed what happens
to this space yes things there okay no
problem okay it will stay there and tell
another planet comes okay got it
that space is it negative
yeah it's an absence of stuff you see
it's the absence of physical stuff it's
the physical stuff which is absent could
exist or could not exist it exists okay
so that's not emptiness emptiness must
be the absence of something which could
not exist like a husband who didn't come
from you
okay the absence in your kitchen of a
husband who didn't come from your seats
is real emptiness does that help you
that's another test of whether you saw
emptiness or not okay whether you're
thinking correctly or not doesn't help
you to know there's space here and a
space is still there will it make you
successful financially not really it
doesn't help you will it solve your
marriage problem no that that's another
sign that's not emptiness does the blue
sky help your marriage problem not
really does outer space help your
marriage problem yes if you can send
your husband there
some guys have my okay my okay now last
kind of space right it's the husband in
your kitchen who yells at you that
didn't come from you that didn't come
from you okay that one's impossible the
emptiness of that is real emptiness okay
now if we're the devil and we want to
waste people's life let's teach them
space like meditation on the first three
let's make them waste their time stare
at the blue sky close your eyes think of
blacks
okay or you know what the place where
you are is empty well you're sitting
right now think about it put your mind
on I that's so cool okay
these are let's see if they come okay
let's see if they come okay first one
here we go some people say and there's
no edges there's no middle emptiness of
space mix that with the mind and they
think okay they are go directly to
number three okay
emptiness of place okay they think
that's the emptiness meditation okay
verse 115 then he says the devil says I
can't imagine why anybody should think I
cannot continue in a mind which is
thinking about where's the cup not you
know how's that supposed to hurt me it
doesn't hurt me okay I'm the guy who
says your husband comes from him okay I
don't care if you think about where's
the cop or where's the cups non I don't
care you go ahead
it doesn't hurt me okay got it that's
the the measure of a good meditation is
does it hurt the demo and that's it okay
directly or indirectly okay so I
continue 1/16 my delightful dance here
within the mind okay you go ahead you
focus on that where the cup was I love
it I will dance while you go to hell
okay let's go to hell together I'll
Drive this mine to the hell realms you
know let's go
if you think you can even touch me that
way yeah you're idiot okay yeah fool
okay and you go to any monastery you go
to any temple probably you'll hear one
of these okay you check it out okay you
check it out
all right next one is is it verse number
117 some people think it's a meditation
on the way things really are
that's a synonym for emptiness okay the
way things really are is the synonym for
emptiness in common uh Sheila we're
gonna learn a long list of different
words for emptiness okay the way things
really are is a synonym for emptiness
okay so some people say just watch a
thought pop up stare at its arrival now
we're going down to 118 and when it
slips away this is the Buddhist body of
reality this is the core of the Buddha
this is the emptiness in the lamas heart
right at the very end of the
lion stance okay this is that emptiness
in the lion's heart okay what thoughts
come from nowhere and they go to nowhere
okay in common last Sheila we're gonna
talk about it okay
clouds just form in the sky they don't
like come from Wilcock go down the
highway and then turn off at their mom
they just come and then they leave okay
they just disappear okay so if you watch
a thought come into your mind like a
clown and you watch a thought go out of
your mind like a clown
that's the emptiness of the Buddha they
say that okay then the devil says that's
cool so the more random thoughts you
have the more Buddha bodies your scene
let's have as many random thoughts as we
can you know just think about what
you're going to do next week and the
week after that worry about people you
haven't met yet get angry at your
ex-wife or ex-husband think about them
all the time and each time that thought
comes in and goes out you saw another
Buddha this is cool okay alright so keep
thinking about all those Buddha bodies I
love it 1:19 you just think about how
the mind is not physical and you think
this is gonna hurt me it's nothing but a
joke okay Cayman and Cayman a it's a
joke yeah this is a big joke come on
kidding you must be kidding me okay you
must be kidding me - Allah loves yoga
huh he's a joke man he was he kidding me
okay
okay now this is where we stopped at at
the college the other last week way back
long ago at the college last week we got
to this one now this takes them this is
difficult okay the Buddha said the more
kinds of proof you used to see emptiness
the better is your mind okay
intelligent people want more reasons why
emptiness exists intelligent people
don't want one explanation they want a
hundred explanations okay they want to
go to commerce the other one then they
want to go to commerce you know -
they'll come a sheet of 24 okay and
they're happy because it's more it's
more reasons for meditation okay now one
of the most famous reasons for emptiness
is called the cheated I'll say cheek -
down cheek means things are not one and
things are not many
therefore they are empty okay things are
not one and things are not many
therefore they are empty okay and there
are many misunderstandings of this proof
so the lower-middle way school likes
this proof okay it's in the ACI course -
also okay it's in ACI course - also you
know consider Luka she she doesn't exist
ultimately because she's not ultimately
one and she's not ultimately many
okay so we're gonna talk about it a lot
in common uh Sheila okay we're gonna
talk about it a lot this kind of proof
we're gonna talk about it a lot okay
she's not ultimately many that's easy
because she's not many she's only one
Luka okay that part's easy okay she's
not to Lucas she's one Luka okay that
part's easy is she one Luca one whole
Luca you see if she is ultimately from
her own side
she shouldn't have parts okay that we
have to talk about it okay she shouldn't
have a left ear and a right ear and a
left eye and the right eye okay her
right eye should be her left eye her
right ear should be her left ear okay
like this there are many it's a long
story we'll talk about an income unless
you know so in meditation number
thirteen some do a perfect analysis
verse one twenty on the fact that things
are neither one nor many they use it to
find the thing which is not there which
is emptiness but that's a meditation on
the general principle and not on the
proposal okay so this is a logic word
what's the general principle consider
Luca she's not she doesn't exist from
her own sign because she's not one thing
that exists from her own side and she's
not more than one thing which exists
from one side okay what's the what am I
trying to prove she doesn't exist from
her own side that in logic there are
three parts okay afternoon is the worst
time to do lodging you're already asleep
before we did lodgings
I'll take a break after this okay just
stay with me for five minutes I promise
a break you can even have a nappy nap
okay
what's the subject that we are talking
about Luca let's talk about Luca okay
she doesn't come from her own side
because she's not one thing that comes
from her own son and she's not many
things who come from her own side okay
like that now does the other guy agree
to number one and number two I'll say it
again
let's take Luca she doesn't come from
her own son
does he agree no he doesn't it's what
we're trying to prove okay so by
definition he doesn't accept that okay
logic statement syllogism first two
parts the other guy doesn't agree yet
take Luca she doesn't exist the way you
thought she did why why you say that
getting Michael because she's not one
thing that exists that way and she's not
more than one thing that doesn't that
existed okay got it
so one and two he doesn't agree to yet
this is called the proposition this is
what we're trying to prove okay in
Tibetan is called Dube John okay Don
McCarty right and then that's the
opponent that's the other guy believe
one is three she's not one that's coming
from her own side and she's not many
which is coming from her own side does
he already accept that he's supposed to
okay he's supposed to
it's called choke to choke - okay if and
we'll study it someday okay if you live
long enough I will teach you Kato PJ it
would take about 15 years okay and it's
beautiful okay take one
it's two because of three okay the
opponent must agree one is three Luca is
not one thing that comes from its own
side
or more than one thing which comes from
in something he already accepts that he
must already accept that or it's a bad
reason
okay now okay here we go if the other
guy are they self one is three and he
meditates on that will it give him new
insight no he already accepts them he
already understood that okay so in this
meditation in bad meditation number
third team the other guy already saw
that things don't come one Luca is not
one thing that comes from herself and
she's not more than one thing that comes
he already saw that okay so that's not
gonna push the devil out of your mind
okay he already accept that and he has
the devil in this mine okay okay it's a
logic thing okay it's a logic thing this
is interesting when you're trying to
prove something to somebody the reason
must be something they already accept
but they didn't think about that it
proves what you're saying okay give me
anything we should go to the Japanese
restaurant tonight because you were like
okay this is logic for your wife or your
husband
we should eat Japanese food tonight and
she says why and Nick says let's go to
Japanese food Aaron says why and then
Nick says cuz you're gonna love it okay
so does does he believe she accepts that
the Japanese restaurant is something she
would love yes you are an exception okay
does Aaron accept that if she loves the
Japanese restaurant three then two we
should go yeah she accept that if it's a
place she love she will love she will
agree we should go she accepts one is
three
the Japanese restaurant is someplace I'm
I might like okay sorry
take the Japanese restaurant we should
go there because you would like it she's
supposed to agree with him that it's
possible I would like the Japanese
restaurant one is three okay now we call
the reverse if three then two if if
Aaron will love the Japanese restaurant
we should go she accepts that okay but
so far she didn't tie up together that
we should go to the restaurant got it
okay she accepts the lodging but she
didn't think about it yet okay that's
the only kind of logic which correct
okay I'll say it again Nick says to
Aaron let's let's let's talk about you
and me we should go to the Japanese
restaurant why you will love it okay if
she would love it should they go yeah is
it possible she would love it yeah but
she didn't agree yet to this then we
should go you see that's what logic is
for to convince your wife you're right
that's the only reason for lodging okay
in this meditation then the guy already
is meditating about something he already
understood okay take Luca she's not one
impossible thing and she's not to
impossible thing he understands that
okay he believes done it's it's looking
1 impossible thing no she's sitting
right here just kick anybody who says
yes okay don't worry it won't hurt
because she's impossible
it's Luca an impossible thing no is she
more than one imposter she 2 or 3
impossible things no why well cuz she's
not one impossible thing geshe-la how
can she be - okay all right
now if you understood that
that she's not impossible you already
know that and you think about that will
you become a Buddha okay take Luca she's
not one impossible thing and guess what
she's not more than one impossible thing
if you understand that do you become
Buddha no it's not enough okay that's
all that's all that's the point of this
meditation
it doesn't hurt him it doesn't hurt the
devil he knew she was not impossible he
already knew that okay it doesn't prove
anything okay the restaurant is
someplace you might like yeah I
understand oh so what okay I understand
it doesn't prove anything yet okay all
right I'm sorry to do this to you in the
afternoon okay let's do one more just so
you can go to the bathroom in peace okay
number fourteen bad meditation number 14
verse 121
when you see your llama in the
meditation and the seeds are opening up
okay
the seeds are opening up and you see a
llama who's coming from your seats okay
have you seen emptiness good now next
question when you see your llama cannot
be the llama who's not coming from you
do you see emptiness when you see your
llama is not accidental
do you see emptiness yeah you do
that's emptiness the llama who's not not
coming from you is emptiness okay
any llama who's not coming from you boo
boo llama you cancel that one that's
emptiness okay to think that the llama
is coming from your seeds is that
emptiness not yet okay not yet okay got
it
so first pension llamas trying to be
very clear during meditation number nine
there are four parts who can tell me the
first one just think of some good
quality about your number any good
quality okay they eat pizza really well
it's true okay
second thing yeah the quality is coming
out of my state their college community
what's the third part make a story about
your past life make a story my past life
okay then the last part try to imagine a
llama without that story and there's no
such number okay which one is emptiness
only the fourth one only the last one
okay the ones before that are what do we
call them in Buddhism wait if you tell
me correctly you can have a pee-pee
break what's the first three car yeah
who said that okay you get to have a
pee-pee break everybody else has to stay
huh yeah when you go into it directly as
a negation it is a negation in your mind
at the negation you're canceling the
Lama who came from you that's true the
thought itself is non emptiness the
perception of emptiness is not emptiness
emptiness is the object of the
perception of emptiness but the
perception of emptiness is not ultimate
reality it's deceptive reality okay okay
take a break 15 minutes
okay I'm gonna cover one more verse then
if you have some small questions okay
21:21
some do the analysis of one of many and
I'm gonna cover that analysis during
Camila Sheila it will take I have a
hundred and forty pages of notes okay it
will take a while okay but some people
do that analysis and then they think
there's no me right Michael because
Michael exists because Michael was given
a name okay Michael exists when you give
Michael a name then that helps Michael
to exist so they think if you meditate
that Michael got the name Michael and
that created Michael they think you are
seeing emptiness okay what's the
difference between the hologram that
comes out of the scene to to llama to
your llama okay see it opens picture
comes out and goes on your llama and
then you see they are honest or they are
happy person or something okay what's
the difference between that and the name
happy is it the same thing in Buddhism
we say it it it's almost the same thing
what when that picture that comes out in
not mind it's the true name true name
okay
not the sound ma that's just a sound but
when you when you think Geshe Michael
and that thought comes out of your mind
creates Geshe Michael that's what we
call in Buddhism a true word the real
word Christian Bible start
yeah in the beginning was the word very
interesting okay so picture came out in
mind we have to talk about during Camila
Sheila what's the difference between
name and that picture okay
what's a difference is that the true
name is that the real name okay we have
talked about so anyway this guy
meditation number fourteen okay there's
gonna be ten
it's gonna be eleven that we don't reach
today they just meditate on that name
came out and covered gushy Michael and
now we think of Geshe Michael okay and
that to them that's emptiness meditation
okay then the devil says that it makes
me uncomfortable but it doesn't
contradict me okay you you're not
thinking about the Michael who exists
without a name okay say again it means
this all but but this it means but this
it's dull education Michael's grammar
you can say but this is not a minute
this is a meditation okay this is
difficult do you want to go there I
can't believe it
in the afternoon it's Geshe Michael
president the United States right now no
okay
that's called a negative of not being
something okay that's called identity
negative of identity in English you say
he is not the president okay is not in
English that's a negative but it's
negative about who is guess you Michael
he is not president okay got it now
there's a second kind of negative that
that in Tibetan that's called main gun
the second kind of negative called mega
Geshe Michaels not in the kitchen right
now okay that's an absence okay it's not
talking geshe michael is present in our
guest Michael's not present it just mean
in the kitchen
Geshe Michael is not there absent okay
it's emptiness the first kind of
negative or the second kind of negative
second kind okay second kind so if you
think of some kind of Geshe Michael is
not something okay and you think about
that that's not emptiness yet okay
that's not emptiness yet it's the first
kind of negative it's not the same kind
of negative okay that's what we're
talking about here number fourteen you
are thinking about you're looking at
geshe-la does he exist without a name
well we say no because name is the
picture the real name is the picture
okay can't guess you know exist without
the picture coming from you yeah cannot
exist okay
is geshe-la a non picture person no he's
a picture person
okay now if I say - lies not this nice
it's not a non picture person okay it's
not quite emptiness yet okay it's not
quite emptiness yet you have to say it a
little bit differently geshe-la a a
theoretical geshe-la who didn't come
from me who didn't come from my name
doesn't exist
that's emptiness okay that's emptiness
okay that's a little subtle okay that's
a little stuff again emptiness should be
the absence of something which cannot
exist geshe-la without a name meaning -
not without picture come from you cannot
exist okay that's emptiness that makes
the devil uncomfortable if you start to
think about that he gets uncomfortable
but if you just see geshe-la is not the
kind of person who doesn't come from
seeds you are watching - now come from
seeds it's not emptiness yet okay
I can do questions or we can do another
stupid meditation what do you want to do
you want to go ahead okay let's go yeah
you'll have to change time okay number
is it a meditation on Geshe Michaels
emptiness if you close your eyes and you
pretend Geshe Michaels not in the room
that's pretty easy okay then if you
think that's emptiness you are wandering
further and further away from emptiness
verse 124 and then he's he says by the
way emptiness is always right in front
of you okay it's all around you all the
time
frustrating isn't it if you see it
directly for 20 minutes you you will
become a Buddha in not very long and
it's around you all the time okay if you
don't use an antidote against me okay
what's the antidote there's no booboo
Lama okay if you don't use that antidote
against me then what do you want me to
do I have to stay here there's no choice
I also can't leave even if I want to
leave I cannot okay if you keep thinking
about wrong kind of emptiness don't
blame me okay I have to stay what else
am I gonna do okay that's your fault
it's not my fault okay your problems
your fault you didn't meditate level 9
don't blame it on me
I live here my whole life okay then you
want to kick me out kick me out but if
you don't kick me out then don't blame
me that's your problem
okay got it who's talking demo okay good
number sixteen verse number 125 then
this is called suspending your mind
don't have any opinion is Luka one is
look at two it's look at impossible one
it's looking impossible too I don't know
you know I don't want to fight with
anybody I'm a real Buddhist we just make
friends with everybody you know I I want
to think about it it's too complicated
okay
is she impossible one why do you want to
talk about that who cares okay I don't
want to think about it okay
is that an emptiness meditation no okay
they say don't think about anything and
you've reached some deep meditation okay
then he says you can give that
meditation some big name like zolpe Chen
or you can make up some big name Maha
mudra joke ten Vipassana you can call it
anything you want some big name he says
big name but it doesn't hurt me okay you
could give it some fancy name it doesn't
hurt me okay call it some you know
Transcendental Meditation I don't care
you call it any big thing you want as
long as you're just thinking about
nothing I'm fine you I'm happy you can
call it anything okay you can call it
Google booboo meditation I don't care
doesn't hurt me okay it gets famous in
the world but it doesn't hurt me I don't
care you can have some meditation
society you can teach that I don't care
go ahead okay all right 127
[Music]
let's just talk about the flow now he
starts talking about the there was a
school in Tibet say watch the flow of
the meditation okay watch the seeds come
out of the mind watch the seeds open
watch them create the Lama okay and just
keep watching this process okay watch
the mind as it creates the Lama okay is
the mind emptiness no even the mind
which sees emptiness is not emptiness
okay if you could watch the mind which
is watching emptiness that's not
emptiness okay that's not even a
negative it's a positive okay so
watching the mind do its thing even when
the mind is proving emptiness is it's
not emptiness itself okay
the mind is not emptiness itself that's
why when you see emptiness directly you
can't think I did it okay because then
you'd be watching myself or in my mind
okay but during the direct procession
emptiness you are focusing on a negative
on an absence okay got it
so if the object of your mind is your
mind you can't be meditating on
emptiness it's not possible because
that's a positive thing okay cool my
lama used to say jasmine is nodding for
everybody okay thank you
oh it's a weird sort of wisdom that
you're meditating on me and making me
your best friend okay that's the devil
okay
haha you want to know what the Tibetan
is and where's that ha ha
third fourth line 1:28 ha ha very funny
okay what's the mine yeah that's
emptiness oh oh is conking yeah yeah
yeah go ahead it doesn't bother me okay
is it close to emptiness it's pretty
close I mean when you're watching the
scenes you're pretty close so these are
subtle these are not easy okay it
doesn't mean you shouldn't watch the
scenes but it means you're not finished
yet okay if you made the coffee but they
didn't put the milk in it yet it's not
coffee yet
right depends on what country you're
from okay
haha that's a we have time for one more
okay number 18
then somebody uses the correct reasoning
okay now now first more difficult you
ready you got to the end of level 9 you
try to imagine boo-boo llama and I say
that with respect no I say it with
disrespect that llama doesn't exist
right the llama whose accident okay
wasn't created by your good karma just
got on the bus with you one day by
accident okay you saw Scott was cleaning
out his car he saw a newspaper article
about Geshe Michael that's the true
story right then it's just accident if
the newspaper was the other way he
wouldn't be here okay it's just an
accident he meant get my car it's a good
luck he likes to clean out his car okay
in my car I will never meet go see
Michael
then he think about in the meditation is
there a gushing Michael that's not
coming from seeds yes or no no okay then
you're supposed to imagine getting
Michael that you met by accident okay
not because of your karma
okay just catching Michael came to
Guangzhou and you were in the coffee
shop and you saw the sign that Vivian
put there and you went to the talk okay
like okay so when you watch that wrong
Geshe Michael
is that emptiness on meditation not yet
not yet
okay first you have to say he's
impossible then you are meditating on
emptiness okay to imagine getting
Michael that you met by accident to
imagine such a guessing Marco
that's not emptiness yeah that's the
second husband okay that's just the
second husband okay you didn't cancel
him yet you didn't throw the second
husband out of your house yet who's the
second husband the one who's not my
fault he didn't come from me yelling at
my kids last week yeah I didn't do
anything
yeah I didn't do anything okay now now
we're getting closer and closer to
correct emptiness we're getting closer
and closer to correct emptiness now
listen carefully and don't make a
boo-boo about the boo-boo Dahmer Gacy
Michael says imagine a teacher in your
life or your mom or Dunn who came to you
by accident okay try to imagine it then
you say feels bad Geshe Michael I don't
like it try to imagine a llama that you
don't have a relationship with for the
next thousand years like try to imagine
just accident you came to Diamond
Mountain the plane landed here plane
take you back to your country and that's
the end of it there's no connection
there's no mysticism there's no beauty
there's no story
there's no they're not gonna make a
movie about it later
it's just boo-boo you met you you cross
and you go somewhere else okay imagine
that Lama now cancel it
okay cancel it it's wrong it feels wrong
right you met your mother by accident
you met your llama by accident you are
with your Dharma brothers and sisters
it's no magic in this room it's just
boring normal okay then you should say
ah forget that guy see Michael I would
like a romance I like a cool story we
are all like met each other in the past
life we were in India together and
probably we're all sitting in caves
together okay but this boring accident
meeting each other I don't like it okay
okay now you cancel that one that's
impossible
where are you that's emptiness that's
real emptiness okay got it
now one more step here one more step
here should you watch that emptiness or
should you watch yourself watching the
emptiness good okay just watching your
mind watching that emptiness you lost
the emptiness because the mind is not
empty unless it's the afternoon and it's
the end of the class I'll say it again
I'll say it again this is subtle these
are subtle this devil is not stupid lazy
guy he's pretty cool okay I'll say it
again you reach them finally you go
through those eight you reached number
nine seeds open blah blah blah blah past
life meditate on an accident Lama buh
buh buh cancel the accident lover
emptiness boom you're staying in
emptiness okay then you decide to watch
yourself watch the emptiness okay that's
not emptiness that's not emptiness
meditation now question for you if you
watch your mind watch that emptiness can
the devil still stay in your life
okay you can go home nice you you just
finished the class
[Music]